BETH: What is a Behaviour Support Plan?
JOE: Well, it is a plan that contains
a range of strategies which not only
focus on the behaviour that challenges of
individuals with autism, but also includes
ways to ensure that they have access
to things that are important to them.
A behaviour support plan is a
document that is created to help
understand and manage behaviour
in individuals with autism to show
behaviour that others find challenging.
It provides parents and carers with
a step-by-step guide to make sure the
individual has a good quality of life.
BETH: It also enables parents and carers
to identify when intervention is needed
to prevent behaviour that challenges
and help with positive reinforcement.
A good behaviour support plan is based
on the results of a functional assessment
and uses a ‘Positive Behaviour Support’,
a holistic approach which considers not
only the behaviour itself, but also the
circumstances and characteristics of the
individual exhibiting the behaviour and
the people and situations surrounding it.
It’s proactive and preventative,
focusing on the teaching of new skills
to replace behaviours that challenge.
JOE: The plan contains a range of
strategies which not only focus on
the behaviours but also includes ways
to ensure the person has access to
things that are important to them.
These strategies used are referred to
as proactive strategies and reactive
strategies and a good behaviour
support plan has more proactive
strategies than reactive ones.
Proactive strategies are tools
that are used to prevent or avoid
problem behaviour from occurring.
They are introduced before any behaviours
that challenge start and help to
reduce the chances of them occurring.
BETH: This helps to ensure that the focus
of the plan is not just on the behaviour
but also provides ways to support
the individual to have a good life,
enabling them to learn better and more
effective ways of getting what they need.